Guide to the Nina Berberova Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1922-1993; Series II; 10.84' (24 boxes)
  - ARTICLES
    - "Neizvestnoe burime V. Zhabotinskogo," offprint, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 934)
    - "N'iu-Iorkskie vechera," clipping, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 935)
    - "Novye knigi," clipping, 1950 (Box 38, Folder 936)
    - "Ogarev i Gertsen," clipping, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 937)
    - "Orest Adamovich Kiprenskii, 1783-1836," typescript, 1936 (Box 38, Folder 938)
    - "Pis'ma M. V. Dobuzhinskogo k N. N. Berberovoi"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 939)
      - Offprint, 1979 (Box 38, Folder 940)
    - "La poésie russe depuis 1917," clipping, 1950 (Box 38, Folder 941)
    - "Realisty i simvolisty deviatnadtsatogo veka"
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 942)
      - Photocopy, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 943)
    - "Sentiabr'skii dnevnik," clipping, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 944)
    - "Smert' Anny Grigor'evny"
      - Printed version, photocopy, 1938 (Box 39, Folder 945)
      - "The Death of Anna Grigor'evna," English translation, three typescripts, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 946)
      - "Sovetskaia kritika segodnia," printed version, photocopy, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 947)
    - "Tchaikovsky's "Suicide" Reconsidered: A Rebuttal"
      - Typescript and photocopy, 1989 (Box 39, Folder 948)
      - "Pis'mo trekh amerikanskikh pro- fessorov," photocopy of Russian translation, 1989 (Box 39, Folder 949)
      - Research notes and clippings, 1981-88 (Box 39, Folder 950)
    - "Vecher v N'iu-Iorke,", n.d. (Box 39, Folder 951)
    - "Velikii vek," offprint, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 952)
    - "Vozvrashchenie Ogarevoi v Rossiiu," clipping, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 953)
    - "Za rubezhom," clipping, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 954)
  - BOOK REVIEWS
    - "Boris Bozhnev, Borba za nesushchest- vovanie ," printed version, photocopy, 1925 (Box 39, Folder 955)
    - "Andrew Field, Nabokov: His Life in Art, typescript, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 956)
    - "Eugenia Ginzburg, Journey into the Whirlwind ," printed version, photocopy, 1969 (Box 39, Folder 957)
    - "Simon Karlinsky, Marina Cvetaeva: Her Life and Art ," clipping, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 958)
    - "Krug, Al'manakh: kniga 2-aia ," printed version, photocopy, 1937 (Box 39, Folder 959)
    - "Vladimir Nabokov, Speak, Memory ," typescript, 1966 (Box 39, Folder 960)
    - "Boris Poplavskii, V venke iz voska ," printed version, photocopy, 1939 (Box 39, Folder 961)
    - "Carl R. Proffer, Keys to Lolita ," typescript, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 962)
    - "A. I. Remizov, Podstrizhennymi glazami ," printed version, photocopy, 1951 (Box 39, Folder 963)
    - "A. I. Remizov, V rozovom bleske ," printed version, photocopy, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 964)
    - "Pauline de Rothschild, The Irrational Journey ," typescript, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 965)
    - "Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, The First Circle and The Cancer Ward ," clipping (Box 39, Folder 966)
    - "IU. Terapiano, Na vetry ," printed version, photocopy, n.d. (Box 39, Folder 967)
    - "TSekh poetov, Kniga 4-aia ," printed version, photocopy, 1923 (Box 39, Folder 968)
    - "Wisconsin Studies in Contemporary Literature. A Special Number Devoted to Vladimir Nabokov," typescript, 1967 (Box 39, Folder 969)
  - PREFACES AND NOTES TO BOOKS
    Andrey Bely, The First Encounter
    - Typescript, two photocopies, n.d.
    - Research notes, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 972)
    - Synopsis, typescript, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 973)
    - Reviews, 1980 (Box 40, Folder 974)
    - Zinaida Gippius, Peterburgskie dnevniki (1914-1919)
      - Printed version of preface, photocopy, 1990 (Box 40, Folder 975)
      - Research notes, 1980, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 976)
    - V. F. Khodasevich, Izbrannaia proza
      - Typescript of notes, photocopy, ca. 1982 (Box 40, Folder 977)
  - TRANSLATIONS
    - Russian translation of Gottfried August Burger's "Lenore," offprint, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 978)
    - Russian translations of poems by Constantine Cavafy, typescript, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 979)
    - Russian translations of poems by T. S. Eliot
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 980)
      - Research notes and clippings (Box 40, Folder 981)
    - Russian translation of "Un pauvre honteux" by Xavier Forneret, typescript, 1945 (Box 40, Folder 982)
    - Russian translations of poems by Goethe, holograph, 1922 (Box 40, Folder 983)
    - Russian translation of a poem by Stéphane Mallarmé, holograph, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 984)
    - English translation of Vladimir Belsky's libretto based on Pushkin's "Zolotoi petushok," typescript, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 985)
    - English translation of "Nina Berberova" in Gleb Struve's Russkaia literatura v izgnanii (1956), typescript, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 986)
    - English translation of Marius Petipas' libretto of "The Nutcracker," typescript, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 987)
    - French translation of Dostoevsky's Vechnyi muzh, printed version, 1947 (Box 40, Folder 988)
    - French translation, Jules Margoline's La condition inhumaine, printed version, 1949 (Box 40, Folder 989)
    - Other translations, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 990)
    - Research notes on translating, n.d. (Box 40, Folder 991)
  - LECTURES
    - "The younger generation of the Russian emigration", 1923 (Box 41, Folder 992)
    - "Tchaikovsky", 1938 (Box 41, Folder 993)
    - List of public lectures, n.d. (Box 41, Folder 994)
    - "65 Years of Soviet Literature", 1967 (Box 41, Folder 995)
    - "Tolstoy after Anna Karenina", 1981 (Box 41, Folder 996)
    - "The British Ancestors of Nabokov", 1983 (Box 41, Folder 997)
  - COURSE PLANS
    - Exams, n.d. (Box 41, Folder 998)
    - "Dostoevsky", 1983 (Box 41, Folder 999)
    - "History of Russian Literary Criticism"
      - Lecture notes, undated (Box 77, Folder 1493-1494)
      - "The Thaw in Soviet Literary Criticism", 1977, undated (Box 77, Folder 1495)
      - "Aesthetics", undated (Box 77, Folder 1496)
      - "Veselovskii", undated (Box 77, Folder 1497)
      - "Philosophical criticism", undated (Box 77, Folder 1498)
      - "Biographical notes", undated (Box 77, Folder 1499)
      - "Symbolism", undated (Box 77, Folder 1500)
      - "Psychoanalytics", undated (Box 77, Folder 1501)
      - "Formalism", undated (Box 77, Folder 1502)
      - "Annenskii", undated (Box 77, Folder 1503)
      - "Blanc Verse [Belye Stikhi]", undated (Box 77, Folder 1504)
      - "Aleksandr Blok", undated (Box 77, Folder 1505)
      - "Chekhov", undated (Box 77, Folder 1506)
      - "Viacheslav Ivanov", n.d. (Box 77, Folder 1507)
      - "Remizov", n.d. (Box 77, Folder 1508)
      - "Prosody and Poetics" (Box 77, Folder 1509)
      - "Poetical translation", n.d. (Box 77, Folder 1510)
      - Symbolism, n.d. (Box 77, Folder 1511-1512)
    - "Nabokov", n.d. (Box 41, Folder 1000-1001)
    - "Poetry", 1982 (Box 41, Folder 1002-1003)
    - "Russian Emigre Literature", n.d. (Box 41, Folder 1004)
    - "Structuralism in Poetics"
      - French critics, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1005)
      - After Formalism, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1006)
      - Propp and Levi-Strauss (Box 42, Folder 1007)
      - Ferdinand de Saussure (Box 42, Folder 1008)
      - Prague and the Thirties (Box 42, Folder 1009)
      - Jakobson, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1010)
      - Jean Cohen, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1011)
      - Genette and Germany (Box 42, Folder 1012)
      - Theory, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1013)
      - Soviet Critics, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1014)
    - "Symbolism", n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1015)
    - "Tolstoy after Anna Karenina", 1975, n.d. (Box 42, Folder 1016-1017)
  - WRITINGS BY OTHERS ABOUT BERBEROVA'S LIFE AND WORK
    - Reviews
      - Bound volumes of blurbs and reviews of various works, compiled by Actes Sud, 1986-89 (Box 43, Folder 1018-1021)
      - Bound volumes, continued, 1989 (Box 44, Folder 1022)
      - General book reviews on Berberova's works (Box 44, Folder 1023)
    - General articles on Berberova's life
      - English press, 1950-93 (Box 44, Folder 1024-1025)
      - French press, 1950-93 (Box 44, Folder 1026-1027)
      - German press, 1989-91 (Box 44, Folder 1028)
      - Italian press, 1991-93 (Box 44, Folder 1029)
      - Russian press, 1950-93 (Box 44, Folder 1030-1031)
      - Other, 1946-93 (Box 44, Folder 1032)
- Subject Files, 1934-1993; Series III; 1.50' (3 boxes)
  Series III, Subject Files, is organized into two subseries: Individuals and Organizations, and Topical.
  - INDIVIDUALS AND ORGANIZATIONS
    - Akhmatova, Anna, 1948 (Box 45, Folder 1033)
    - Allilueva, Svetlana, 1984-85 (Box 45, Folder 1034)
    - Ardis Publishers, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1035)
    - Belinkov, Arkadii, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1036)
    - Billington, James H., 1968-91 (Box 45, Folder 1037)
    - Blok, Liubov', n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1038)
    - Boswell, James, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1039)
    - Brodsky, Joseph, 1971-85, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1040)
    - Bunin, Ivan, 1950-84 (Box 45, Folder 1041)
    - Burgina, Anna Mikhailovna, 1984 (Box 45, Folder 1042)
    - Camus, Albert, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1043)
    - Drouet, Juliette, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1044)
    - Eitingon, Max, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1045)
    - Freud, Sigmund (Box 45, Folder 1046)
    - Gippius, Zinaida, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1047)
    - Gorky, Maxim, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1048)
    - Hepburn, Katharine, 1991 (Box 45, Folder 1049)
    - Institute of Modern Russian Culture, 1980-89 (Box 45, Folder 1050)
    - Jakobson, Roman, 1972, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1051)
    - Jawlensky, Alexei, 1979, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1052)
    - Karlinsky, Simon, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1053-1054)
    - Karpovich, Michael, 1959 (Box 45, Folder 1055)
    - Kennan Institute for Advanced Russian Studies, 1978-93, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1056)
    - Kerensky, Aleksandr (Box 45, Folder 1057)
    - Kerensky, Therese, 1946 (Box 45, Folder 1058)
    - Kristeva, Julia, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1059)
    - Kudasheva, Mariia, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1060)
    - Levi-Strauss, Claude, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1061)
    - Liberman, Conrad, 1989 (Box 45, Folder 1062)
    - Lourié, Arthur, n.d. (Box 45, Folder 1063)
    - Makeev, Nikolai Vasil'evich, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1064)
    - Mandel'shtam, Osip, 1979, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1065)
    - Matisse, Henri, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1066)
    - Mayakovsky, Vladimir, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1067)
    - Mel'chuk, Igor, 1978-84 (Box 46, Folder 1068)
    - Miloshenskii, Vladimir, 1971 (Box 46, Folder 1069)
    - Mirsky, D. S., n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1070)
    - Monod, Jacques, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1071)
    - Moskovskii novodevichii monastyr', n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1071a)
    - Nappelbaum, Ida, 1986-92, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1072)
    - Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1961-91, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1073)
    - Nyssen, Hubert, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1074)
    - Oppenheimer, Robert, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 1075)
    - Orwell, George, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1076)
    - Pasternak, Boris Leonidovich, 1959, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1077)
    - Pivot, Bernard, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1078)
    - Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich (Box 46, Folder 1079)
    - Remizov, Aleksei, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1080)
    - Sartre, Jean-Paul, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1081)
    - Siniavskii, Andrei, 1965-77, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1082)
    - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr Isaevich (Box 46, Folder 1083)
    - Stolitsa, Liubov', 1934 (Box 46, Folder 1084)
    - Strada, Vittorio, 1986-87 (Box 46, Folder 1085)
    - Stravinsky, Igor, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1086)
    - Temkina, Marina, 1992 (Box 46, Folder 1087)
    - TSvetaeva, Marina, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1088)
    - Urin, Viktor, 1991 (Box 46, Folder 1089)
    - Wilson, Edmund (Box 46, Folder 1090)
    - Yourcenar, Marguerite, 1987-89, n.d. (Box 46, Folder 1091)
    - Zaitsev, Boris, 1951-61 (Box 46, Folder 1092)
  - TOPICAL
    - Aging and Death (Box 47, Folder 1093)
    - American Literary Criticism, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1094)
    - Bisexuality and Open Marriages (Box 47, Folder 1095)
    - Bourgeoisie, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1096)
    - French Literary Criticism, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1097)
    - German Occupation, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1098)
    - Literary Terminology, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1099)
    - Literature, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1100)
    - Philosophy, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1101)
    - Physics, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1102)
    - Religion, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1103)
    - Russia, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1104)
    - Russian Archival Material, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1105)
    - Russian Emigres, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1106-1107)
    - Russian Operas, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1108)
    - Russian Writers and Poets (Box 47, Folder 1109-1110)
    - Sovremennye zapiski, 1990 (Box 47, Folder 1111)
    - Structuralism, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1112-1113)
    - Syntaxis, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1114)
    - Theater, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1115)
    - United States, n.d. (Box 47, Folder 1116)
    - Western Writers and Poets (Box 47, Folder 1117)
- Personal Papers, 1916-1993; Series IV; 2.25' (5 boxes)
  Series IV, Personal Papers, is organized into six subseries: Personal Documents, Publishers/Publishing, Dedications and Inscriptions, Diaries, Calendars and Address Book, Papers Concerning Vladislav Khodasevich, and Other Papers.
  - PERSONAL DOCUMENTS
    - Bank statements, 1989-90 (Box 48, Folder 1118-1119)
    - Cancelled checks, 1980-90 (Box 48, Folder 1120)
    - Divorce papers, 1982-83 (Box 48, Folder 1121)
    - Financial logs, 1986-91 (Box 48, Folder 1122-1123)
    - Honorary degrees
      - Glasboro State College, diploma, 1980 (Box 48, Folder 1124)
      - Middlebury College, diploma, 1983 (Box 48, Folder 1125)
      - Middlebury College, President's speech to NNB, 1983 (Box 48, Folder 1126)
      - Yale University, diploma, 1992
      - Yale University, commencement program, 1992 (Box 48, Folder 1127)
    - Identification cards, 1984-90 (Box 48, Folder 1128)
    - Medical records, 1989-92 (Box 48, Folder 1129)
    - Passports, 1950-87 (Box 48, Folder 1130)
    - Tax return documents, 1991-92 (Box 48, Folder 1131)
    - Visa documents, 1989 (Box 48, Folder 1132)
  - PUBLISHERS/PUBLISHING
    - Actes sud (Publishers), 1988-91, n.d. (Box 49, Folder 1133-1135)
    - Russica Publishers, 1980-88 (Box 49, Folder 1136)
    - Other, 1964-89 (Box 49, Folder 1137-1139)
  - DEDICATIONS AND INSCRIPTIONS
    - List of poems dedicated to Berberova, n.d. (Box 49, Folder 1140)
    - Gumilev's inscription, 1916 (Box 49, Folder 1141)
    - Khodasevich's inscriptions to Berberova, 1924-30 (Box 49, Folder 1142)
  - DIARIES, CALENDARS, ADDRESS BOOKS
    - Diaries, 1960-86 (Box 50, Folder 1143-1152)
    - Diaries, continued, 1986-93 (Box 51, Folder 1153-1155)
    - Calendar, 1973 (Box 51, Folder 1156)
    - Address books, n.d. (Box 51, Folder 1157-1159)
    - Desk calendar, 1993
  - PAPERS CONCERNING VLADISLAV KHODASEVICH
    - NNB's List of correspondence between Khodasevich and Gippius (Box 52, Folder 1160)
    - NNB's summary of the illness and death of Khodasevich, holograph and copy, 1939 (Box 52, Folder 1161)
    - Obituaries of Khodasevich, clippings, 1939 (Box 52, Folder 1162)
    - NNB's analysis of some of Khodasevich's poetry, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1163)
    - NNB's bibliography of articles by Khodasevich, 1969 (Box 52, Folder 1164)
    - Papers regarding the restoration of Khodasevich's gravesite, 1982 (Box 52, Folder 1165)
    - NNB's copy of Sobranie stikhov, with Khodasevich's handwritten comments, 1927 (Box 52, Folder 1166)
    - Reprints of two articles by Khodasevich, 1989 (Box 52, Folder 1167)
    - Article on Khodasevich by Sofiia Parnok, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1168)
    - NNB's notes about Khodasevich, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1169)
    - Clippings, photocopies about Khodasevich, 1956-89, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1170-1172)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - NNB's membership card for the Petersburg Union of Poets signed by Nikolai Gumilev and Georgii Ivanov, 1921 (Box 52, Folder 1173)
    - NNB's invitation from Zinaida Gippius to the inauguration of Merezhkovsky's monument, 1943 (Box 52, Folder 1174)
    - Resume, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1175)
    - Topical notes, 1970, n.d. (Box 52, Folder 1176)
    - Miscellaneous personal reminders, receipts, maps and other papers (Box 52, Folder 1177-1179)
    - List of unannotated books and serials removed from NNB's apartment but not retained by the library (Box 52, Folder 1179a)
- Photographs, 1913-1993; Series V; 1.0' (2 boxes)
  Series V, Photographs, is organized into six subseries: Berberova's Family, Portraits of Berberova, Snapshots of Berberova, Other People, Places, and Other.
  - BERBEROVA'S FAMILY
    - Parents, grandparents, cousin, 1913-2? (Box 53, Folder 1180)
  - PORTRAITS OF BERBEROVA
    - At age 12 and age 24, 1913-25 (Box 53, Folder 1181)
    - Passport photos, 1950-77 (Box 53, Folder 1182)
    - At the Smithsonian, 1978 Sep (Box 53, Folder 1183)
    - At Yaddo, 1963 (Box 53, Folder 1184)
    - By Agence Photographique, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1185)
    - By Jacques Aucagos, 1986 (Box 53, Folder 1186)
    - By S. Bassauls, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1187)
    - By Kathleen Blumenfeld, 1989-92 (Box 53, Folder 1188)
    - By Jack Deaso, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1189)
    - By A. Nikolaev, 1989 (Box 53, Folder 1190)
    - By Arturo Patten, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1191-1192)
    - By John Phillips, 1991 (Box 53, Folder 1193)
    - By Orren Jack Turner, 1964 (Box 53, Folder 1194)
    - By unidentified photographers, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1195)
  - SNAPSHOTS OF BERBEROVA
    - Berberova Alone
      - At the Kravchenko trial, 1948 (Box 53, Folder 1196)
      - Honorary degree at Glasboro State University, 1980 (Box 53, Folder 1197)
      - Honorary degree at Middlebury College, 1983 (Box 53, Folder 1198)
      - Honorary degree and 90th birthday dinner at Yale University, 1991-92 (Box 53, Folder 1199)
      - Trip to Soviet Union, 1989 (Box 53, Folder 1200)
      - In Europe, ca. 1939-47, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1201)
      - In the U.S., ca. 1950-59 (Box 53, Folder 1202)
      - In Longchêne, ca. 1975 (Box 53, Folder 1203)
      - In Philadelphia, ca. 1991-92 (Box 53, Folder 1204)
      - In Princeton, 1983-90 (Box 53, Folder 1205)
      - Other, ca. 1969-87, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1206)
    - Berberova with Others
      - Barker, Murl, 1973-89, n.d. (Box 53, Folder 1207-1208)
      - Bunin, Ivan; Kuznetsova, Galina, 1928 (Box 53, Folder 1209)
      - Deotto, Patrizia, 1992 (Box 53, Folder 1210)
      - Katanian, Vassily, 1986 (Box 53, Folder 1211)
      - Khodasevich, Vladislav Felitsianovich, 1922-39 (Box 53, Folder 1212)
      - Mastroianni, Marcello, 1991 (Box 54, Folder 1213)
      - Misslin, Anne, 1989 (Box 54, Folder 1214)
      - Nyssen, Hubert, 1987-90, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1215-1217)
      - Sheikholeslami, Erika, 1992 (Box 54, Folder 1218)
      - Smakov, Gennady
      - Tolstaya, Alexandra, 195? (Box 54, Folder 1219)
      - Others, 1946-93, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1220-1224)
        Includes Gennady Smakov (folder 1222)
  - OTHER PEOPLE
    - Akhmatova, Anna, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1225)
    - Alonzo, Anne-Marie, 1984, 1988 (Box 54, Folder 1225a)
    - Bely, Andrey (Box 54, Folder 1226)
    - Bogatyreva, Sonia, 1979 (Box 54, Folder 1227)
    - Brik, Lili, 1901 (Box 54, Folder 1228)
    - Brik, Lili; Katanian, Vassily, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1229)
    - Brik, Lili; Mayakovsky, Vladimir, 1924 (Box 54, Folder 1230)
    - Brodsky, Joseph; Anschuetz, Carol, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1230a)
    - Bunin, Ivan; Makeev, Nikolai, 1939 (Box 54, Folder 1231)
    - Dutton, Richard, 1980, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1232)
    - Fischer, Louis, 1968-70 (Box 54, Folder 1233)
    - Gippius, Zinaida, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1234)
    - Gorky, Maxim, 1923-25 (Box 54, Folder 1235)
    - Gurvich, Fira, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1236)
    - Karpovich, Mikhail, 1957 (Box 54, Folder 1237)
    - Katanian, Vassily, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1238)
    - Kerensky, Therese, 1945 (Box 54, Folder 1239)
    - Khatchatrian, Vanda (Box 54, Folder 1240)
    - Klenovskii, Dmitrii Iosifivich, 1961 (Box 54, Folder 1241)
    - Lourié, Vera, 1985 (Box 54, Folder 1242)
    - Makeev, Nikolai, 1963 (Box 54, Folder 1243)
    - Makeeva, Irina, 1990 (Box 54, Folder 1244)
    - Mitterrand, François; Nyssen, Hubert (Box 54, Folder 1245)
    - Nappelbaum, Ida, 1930-89 (Box 54, Folder 1246)
    - Schwartz, Marian, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1247)
    - Sieveking, Edda, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1248)
    - Stolitsa, Liubov', n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1249)
    - Sylvester, Richard, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1250)
    - Task, Sergei, 1981 (Box 54, Folder 1251)
    - Vol'skii, Nikolai Vladislavovich, 1925 (Box 54, Folder 1252)
    - Unidentified, 1927-47, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1253-1255)
  - PLACES
    - Russia, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1256)
    - Smithsonian, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1257)
    - Other locales, n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1258)
  - OTHER
    - Snapshots of drawings and paintings of Berberova (Box 54, Folder 1259)
    - Snapshots of various drawings and paintings (Box 54, Folder 1260)
    - Negative of a print, "Vue du canal de la Moika et du Pont de la Police de St. Petersbourg", n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1261)
- Memorabilia and Personal Effects, 1980-1992; Series VI; 0.75' (1 box)
  - Lock of Khodasevich's hair, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1262)
  - Two franc coins placed on Khodasevich's eyes, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1263)
  - Khodasevich's wallet, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1264)
  - Khodasevich's cigarette case, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1265)
  - Zinaida Gippius' powder box, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1266)
  - Zinaida Gippius' notebook, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1267)
  - Dmitry Merezhkovsky's letter opener, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1268)
  - [Chevalier de l'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres, France]
    - Medal, [1989?] (Box 55, Folder 1269)
    - Certificate, [1989?]
  - NNB's eyeglasses, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1270-1271)
  - Academic Hoods (for honorary degrees received from Yale, Middlebury College and Glasboro State University), 1980-92
  - NNB's black dress, worn when she received the honorary degree from Yale University, n.d.
- Audiovisual Material, 1985-1989; Series VII; 0.50' (1 box)
  - Interview of Berberova by Bernard Pivot, on "Apostrophes," the French television literary talk show, tape 1 of 2, 1989 April; GENMSS182_0001; 1; 02:03:29; There is a hiss in the audio. (Box 56, Item barcode 39002102339109)
  - Interview of Berberova by Bernard Pivot, on "Apostrophes," the French television literary talk show, tape 2 of 2, 1989 April; GENMSS182_0002; 1; 00:59:23; There is a hiss in the audio. (Box 56, Item barcode 39002102339117)
  - Radio interview of NNB on Italian radio (R.S.I./Lugano). Interviewer: Franca Tiberto/MI?. Cassette tape plus reference/use copy, n.d.; 1 (Box 56, Folder 1273)
  - NNB reading her own poetry. Cassette tape, n.d.; 1 (Box 56, Folder 1274)
  - Le mal noir - book on tape, read by Jeanne Moreau. Produced by Actes Sud 2 cassette tapes plus reference/use copy. (total of 4 tapes), n.d.; 4 (Box 56, Folder 1275)
  - Le roseau révolté - book on tape, read by Isabelle Huppert. Produced by Actes Sud (2 cassette tapes), n.d.; 2 (Box 56, Folder 1276)
  - "Presentation de la collection. Bref extraits de cassettes éditées." Fondation Armand Panigel (1 cassette tape), ca. 1985?; 1 (Box 56, Folder 1277)
- Vladislav Khodasevich Papers, 1921-1939; Series VIII; 0.50' (1 box)
  Series VIII, Vladislav Khodasevich Papers, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically within each file.
    - Bakunina, Ekaterina Vasil'evna, 1933 (Box 57, Folder 1279)
    - Bem, A., 1934-38 (Box 57, Folder 1279)
    - Budberg, Moura, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1280)
    - Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich, 1927-39, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1281)
    - Butakova, V., 1935 Jul 17 (Box 57, Folder 1282)
    - Elenev, Nikolai, 1939 May 2 (Box 57, Folder 1283)
    - Epokha, 1923 Mar 27 (Box 57, Folder 1284)
    - Evangulov, Georgii, 1935 Oct 21 (Box 57, Folder 1285)
    - Gershenzon, Mikhail Osipovich, 1921-25 (Box 57, Folder 1286)
    - Gippius, Zinaida, 1925-39, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1287-1290)